All right. Hello, welcome. It is
December 19th, 2025. We are at the
Active Inference Institute quarterly
roundtable number four in 2025. It's
Daniel
and Alexandra
and we are going to jump right in to
this quarterly round table. We're going
to begin with a sort of fresh take
overview, a welcome starting from zero.
Go into some institute updates, project
updates, then look towards 26. Look in
the live chat, see what people have
written and looking forward to it. Okay,
welcome.
Welcome to the active inference
institute. Consider this your pre-flight
onboarding manual before we take flight
into the open skies of the free energy
principle and beyond. The title of each
of these pages is a URL that you can
visit and explore. This is a manual
curation and overview presented in late
2025.
First about the ecosystem at the
institute. Our mission is to promote the
accessibility, applicability, and rigor
of active inference. We exist in
constellation and interaction. We
welcome all to observe at a distance
through publicly available materials to
engage directly through projects,
discord, different programs such as the
internship and fellowship and to get
involved behind the scenes in supporting
all of this as supporter, adviser,
partner, director, etc. We recognize the
broader cosmos of our ecosystem, the
active inference learners, researchers,
practitioners, organizations, and
companies who are co-creating the
present and future of our field.
Participation means you are the chaotic
input to us and possibly us to you. In
this symbiotic relationship, all parties
may either change their minds and change
the world.
Our strategy, our approach is radically
informed by active inference itself. We
embrace open-ended explor exploration as
a fundamental driving force. We
cultivate a culture of curiosity and
continuous learning. Through engaging in
endeavors across multiple scales,
be it person, project, institute or
ecosystem, we enrich our understanding
and contribute to our niche. We see our
actions in light of minimizing free
energy. Much like the equation 2.6 six
in the 2022 textbook consisting of
pragmatic and epistemic value. In doing
so, we carve a path that is both useful
and informative in completing technical,
operational, and even administrative
tasks.
All right, about activities.
There are a variety of weekly meetings
and activities hosted at the institute
and also a bunch of stuff ongoing
asynchronously. Some synchronous events
may be your style or your time zone and
there are ample opportunities to explore
projects on your own time as well.
Admission is free and open to all
educational backgrounds. We invite you
to participate, connect with others,
co-create, learn, and apply active
inference together.
We invite our ecosystem to join us in
setting out their expectations in
planned actions via the preparation
form. We provide a place for you to
inform the community about your ongoing
and upcoming projects. If desired, we
can call out to publicize your project
and attract collaborators. Every journey
begins with preparation, even dreams
that don't leave the base camp.
And in turn, we take measurements to
follow up on our questions and
predictions. We take actions to get new
observations. Submitting a measurement
is the main way that participants in our
ecosystem share updates from their work
for getting visibility, feedback and
collaboration. Measurements are curated
into our monthly newsletter and also
presented on in the quarterly roundts.
Through this prepare measure cycle, we
engage in active inference and co-learn
by doing.
In conclusion, you can reference these
stable links uh throughout the year and
continue to engage with the institute.
To reduce your uncertainty further, you
can email our
blanketactiveinference.institute
email.
Here's some more stable links that you
can always enter into and they'll go to
the most updated version of whatever
that may be.
Some special stable links and topics
that will come up today are the 2025
which was the living entry point for
this year's activity and we'll be
looking towards 2026.
So big picture and what we're excited
for people's live ideas and questions on
and also their emails and other ways of
communicating it is what's next. So
where have we been? Where are we going?
And that brings us to first some updates
at the institute scale. So again taking
a little bit of a fresh look at some
topics that can otherwise be implicit.
We have a annual cycle or rhythm at the
institute and it goes something like
this. In January we start activities
and we start a new cohort of all of the
formal positions. So that's the board of
directors, scientific advisory board and
officers
and weekly activities begin. Broadly
those projects are of two different
types either projects that are open-
source hosted from the institute
long-term stewarded directions like
educational program development ontology
audiovisisual production live streams
and podcasts the journal and knowledge
engineering symposiums the fellows all
of these programs that are held by the
institute as people turn over and then
we provide add visibility, scaffolding
and growing in different kinds of
support for ecosystem projects which are
facilitated by institute affiliated
researchers as well as beyond.
that starts the year and somewhere
around the middle of the year we have a
summer break intermission and then we
largely at the end of the year between
the symposium in around November through
the end of the year have a winterish
break. So January around the dial and
using the year as a convenient uh circle
that we prepare and measure in this
quantum active inference process. We'll
take a moment to appreciate this
beautiful generated art uh with a unique
rhythm of repeating months.
Yes. As as very characteristic so close
yet so far.
And one one example of that a snapshot
was the zenotto
snapshot of our living document which
where many of the stable links will take
you and I'll put that in the live chat
as well and that is kind of a prepare
and measurement annually as we engage in
this multiscale ecoorganizational active
inference process of assessing
directions looking back upon how we did
on them reality ating updating along the
way. So that's a little bit about our
organizational rhythms and now we'll go
into some of the specific updates from
the year on each of these institute
scale programs.
So first in November just a couple weeks
ago we had the fifth applied active
inference symposium and it was a great
time for those who were there. It was
the most numbers of presenters that
we've had, the most number of hours of
content, registrations,
uh getting into the more qualitative,
some of the best pre-symposium
design, publishing, graphic design, the
first sponsors financially that we've
had for the symposium, and the most
engaged and diverse contributions from
the co-organizer team. So I think to
have a takeaway from this kaleidoscope
of 3 days of active inference and little
glimpses into the work and research and
applications of just a subset of the
people working in the field. There's a
lot of fractal space for zooming in for
lower variance events and resources like
a given domain or sector or language or
background or etc. Each of these people
could have been a center of gravity for
a more focused area around their talk.
And also that's kind of what generative
AI is helping us explore. But in terms
of events online and in person, those
are the coming together of the
attention, not just the describing that
you could be in that semantic
neighborhood.
It highlights this emerging
opportunity and need for higher level
opinionation or holding or scaffolding
of different lanes or zones of research
and work like theory, tool development,
different domains of active inference
and what kinds of spaces and ways for
that to all be working in this open
science setting that we're in. So
there's a GitHub repo,
there's a short link that'll take you to
see all of the Applied Active Inference
Symposium programs over the year. And in
terms of ways that you can pick it up
from here, it is definitely not too
early to start organizing for next year.
It is all the more relaxed and chill.
Everyone's welcome to join on this
co-organizing team. any time zone or or
background or way to look at what
happened and give your input on how you
want to make it better next time. We
also have a lot of the input from the
public and also the non-public shared
information on what participants were
interested in, what they'd find helpful
and so on. So get in contact with
symposium in the subject if you want to
get involved on that coorganizing team.
And thanks again to the presenters, the
sponsors, and the co-organizers.
The research fellow
roster slightly grew this year. The
research fellows are individuals
affiliated with the institute. We aim to
support and accelerate their work,
development, and initiatives. So,
previously in the year, Shagger joined
as a research fellow. And in this
quarter, we're happy to announce that we
have two new research fellows, Hongju
and Sheila McCrine. So, you can find
from this link more about all of the
work of these research fellows and their
directions and the program has been
going for almost 2 years now. So, it's
cool to see this incremental growth of
all of these awesome research agendas.
For those who are interested in this
area or this program, consider applying
to be a research fellow. We review those
applications on a rolling basis and
we'll be considering other kinds of
fellows like education application uh as
it might be in the future. Another
option is to join the scientific
advisory board to help review and guide
these applications and provide
mentorship.
You can provide targeted donations to
the projects of the fellows if they've
set that up. And there's a bunch of
other ways that someone could contribute
their feedback to individual fellows in
collaboration and support or at the
program level with the institute.
And one other highlight to call out,
Anna Pereira at the website actin cycle.
Her book navigating uncertainty, simple
active inference and free energy
principles for everyday life has come
out this year with a forward from Carl
Fristen. So for those who are looking
for something readable, explorable,
sharable in that sort of a genre,
definitely check it out. All right.
Partnerships are structured
relationships between the institute and
other organizations who are looking to
make meaningful, visible, custom,
impactful contributions to the active
inference open source ecosystem. We have
three current partners and some in
different stages of development and
that's first principles first, Newman
games and lazy dynamics. So if you are a
organization or an advocate or uh
connector or network weaver and you want
to explore or facilitate a partnership
with the institute and other groups on
some adjacency or area of alignment
definitely get in touch. And this is
going to be one of our priorities to
version and evolve what we can do and
how we set up these partnerships.
Okay. Scientific advisory board. This is
a informal guidance board and in 2025
was composed by these individuals. So,
we'd like to thank over this past
quarter and the year all of the roles
that SAB members played in their
strategic guidance, program development,
symposium participation, and most
recently providing great reviews for
research fellows.
If you're interested in providing some
scientific insight and being a part of
swimming upstream and seeing how you can
get involved in different ways,
definitely consider applying for the
scientific advisory board for next year.
The applications are open till the end
of the year. So, SAB short link and
you'll learn more about these people and
about ways that you can apply for next
year.
And applications are open till December
31st. So you still have time if you're
listening to this live right now.
Okay. Officers and board of directors
are the the formal tactics and strategy
and governance of the institute.
Alexandra and myself are the officers
and we will be continuing on in our
positions next year. We'd also like to
specially thank the 2025 board which was
John Clippinger, Blue Knight, Alex
Vatkin, Daniel Freriedman, Mike Smith,
and Vladimir Bowen. And we will be
providing some information on 2026's
board in the coming weeks.
So, thanks again to the board. And
cool.
Lastly, on this institute scale, support
of the institute is essential as we
build towards a more impactful and
sustainable organization. We're a 501c3
nonprofit and you can go to this
donate.active.institute
link to provide a PayPal donation. You
could support through other financial
affordances like Substack, YouTube, or
you can get involved and help us explore
other ways to connect and and
make our work more robust and available.
Okay, going into a few updates in the
education area. edactive.
First recapping a bit from the middle of
the year, the survival and flourishing
fund fund awarded a $270,000 grant to
the institute to support work on the AI
capabilities and alignment consensus
project AICP.
This is a big team project where Adam
Saffron is the creator, principal
investigator, and organizing editor. So
check out the AICACP short link to learn
more, especially if you're interested in
this AI capabilities and alignment topic
on the textbook group. The textbook
group around the 2022 active inference
textbook has been in continuous
operation from May 2022, shortly after
the book was published on through
basically the end of this year. So
during this year, cohort 8 completed the
book and cohort 9 worked through the
first half. Special thanks to Andrew
Basha for very skilled and caring
facilitation and awesome to see first-
timers and returning textbook group
people. always interesting discussions
and also a good time in the grand scale
of things to look towards the textbook
groups to come which will be next around
this book coming out in March 2026
fundamentals of active inference
principles algorithms and applications
of the free energy principle for
engineers by Sanjie Nam Jooshi so it
will be a great textbook group follow
the textbook hyphen group short link to
register at any time for what we have
going on and get your
attention allocation ready for the
epistemic value of this book to come
which is very eagerly awaited and we
worked with Sanjieve with a group here
in the beta and the versioning of this
textbook so it's going to be a great
work
okay the theoretical neurobiology group
TNB B is been hosted at the institute
during this year. It is the research
discussion and presentation feedback
group for Carl Fristen. And there are a
bunch of ways that you can engage with
this unique and highquality work which
is you can go to the TNB short link or
find theoretical neurobiology on YouTube
where many of the presentations are
available shortly after they are carried
out and also you can join in and join
these meetings actually and it's an
awesome opportunity to step in and to
get involved and see what it's like real
time, ask questions, be a part of the
research itself, connect with Fristan at
all. There's also going to be some
opportunities coming up in the year with
adding and checking metadata to
integrate the records of the TNB from
the years to be integrated with our
journal and knowledge infrastructure. So
if you're interested in that kind of
curation, it is a great way to improve
the indexibility of this work.
And in production news overall, we did
about 72 videos this year overall.
And for the coming year, if you have
skills or interest in audiovisisual,
whether creating new materials,
organizing, panel discussions,
presentations,
any kind of genre, definitely reach out
and we can explore how we can include
that, make it happen on the YouTube
channel in the year to come.
All right, some brief research updates.
The RX Infur project continued to learn
and meet and work with this developing
package and ecosystem around RX infer.jl
which is now in version 4.6.6
at least in checking recently and thanks
to Frasier Patterson for facilitating
the meetings in this last interval. So
check out the package,
learn the topics, learn the background,
see the hashtagengineering channel, and
there's also a separate discord for RX
infer itself. And we look forward to
people using this and other frameworks
to develop all kinds of different works.
Okay,
getting to some of the ecosystem
projects. Just surfacing a couple of the
measurements that were submitted over
the last few days and at any time go to
measure.active inference. Institute and
your updates could also be featured in
this way.
Okay. Interns Harshel Shaw and Satyaki
Mitra reported on their hierarchical
active inference system for autonomous
drone navigation. You can read the full
update here.
Intern Ben Scogorn reports, "I started
publishing my learnings from this year
in a structured way on this website. The
focus was on understanding different
inference methods and models.
Research fellow Jean Francois Clattier
reports after presenting at the annual
applied active inference symposium, I am
back to implementing the presented
design. I'm currently coding in
multi-threaded prologue the phases a
dynam dynamic cognition actor goes
through for each time frame of its
existence and there's a discord channel
with JF discussing this work all the
time
and research fellow John Boy along with
Glenn Repella and Tim Lloyd from the
Cognar ecosystem project report back on
developments related to a white paper
Um so now we look to 2026
uh and consider
what here would be of epistemic and
pragmatic value for you and what else
should we consider and co-explore in the
coming chapter.
So here's our usual closing slide and
here we'll leave it for just a minute on
this visualization. a couple of the ways
that we're looking about what areas to
focus on in the coming year and looking
forward to with the BOD and the SAB
exploring this a lot more in the coming
weeks. So, we'll just review the slides
silently flipping back through for our
visual colleagues. Meanwhile, write in
the chat if you have a comment or a
question and then we'll either explore
it or close it here.
Okay, feel free to continue the
discussion in the Discord or comment
section, email, however. And thank you
all for an awesome year.
Till the next one.